welcome to lecture number 13 about virtualization
so you have the reading instructions as always
and also as always I will start introducing
a bit the topic of this lecture so let's start
with the introduction if you think about a
company that is providing services they can
be digital services or any type of services
basically you know
the most likely they need to keep different
servers different applications so that they
can maintain their own emails they can add
their own webserver an FTP server
an e-commerce service and so on so you are
young and probably what I'm saying sounds
a bit strange but if you think about some
10 15 years
ago the normal way to do this would be to
actually buy a set of physical machines and
set up servers place them in a rack and then
use these dedicated servers one for the email
server one for the web server and so on the
reason here is that sure you could install
all these services in the
same server but at the end of the day you
might need different operating systems for
the different services you might want to have
a machine that has some RAID architecture
and it duplicates all the data on disk for
safety when it comes to emails and the e-commerce
service but maybe for some other thing that's
not needed
maybe you want to have a machine with a very
good network card or connected to a fast switch
when it comes to some kind of service and
so on so the normal thing is that you end
up using several machines
now we will discuss in the next slide that
this has of course good/positive aspects but
also negative ones but the idea with
virtualization it's simple at least theoretically
and notice that virtualization is something that
has been discussed basically for 60 years so
it's not really something new despite the
fact that many advances are
happening right now I mean with the cloud
infrastructures and the recent advancements
let's say the last 10 15 years are
the really good ones in terms of what is available
what you can use nowadays
but now the idea is to create an extra layer
an extra middleware that separates the physical
hardware in this case one single server
this can be called virtual machine monitor but
we call this hypervisor and on top of that
run different operating systems letting
each operating system believe that it's the
only one that
is accessing the physical hardware / the computer / the server you have below
it's not really different conceptually from
the operating system the operating system
does this for the processes the hypervisor
does this for the operating systems that will
do this for the processes
so many aspects we are discussing here
we will see they are connected to what we have
discussed so far so if one wants to think
about benefits and downsides here
if you don't use virtualization so if you
have individual servers for each let's say
service you want to offer
of course you can handle more load if one machine
cannot do everything you can move to a
different machine part of the services
it's more reliable if one server crashes the
others can still work it's also better for
security
so if an intruder manages to corrupt one of
the machines the others might still
be safe as long as they don't suffer from
the same possible problem and of course you
can run different operating systems you have
no restrictions on what you do on the different
computers
but of course this costs a lot of money and
a lot of time because you have to maintain
all the servers on the other end if you go
with virtualization it's still reliable as long as the failures
are happening at the software level if one
operating system crashes the hypervisor can
still let the other operating systems run
and in practice there are higher chances that
a failure happens because of software than
it does because of hardware you can run still
different operating systems that's fine
also the code you really need to maintain
and trust because it's the one that is accessing
the physical hardware is the one of the hypervisor
and the
code of the hypervisor usually does not need
to be as big as the code of the operating
system so it's also easier to maintain it
costs less of course you only have to buy one server it's
also cheaper to try out applications and services
if you want to try a piece of software and
how it works on different operating systems
you don't need to install these on different
servers you can just create an operating
system for a while let the hypervisor run it
and then test your stuff
and actually this is what you use to provide
virtual appliances so if you want to provide
a piece of software that requires a specific
operating system with specific versions of
libraries and so on and so forth you can create
a virtual machine that has the perfect environment
the exact environment you need for that application
install the application and
then give to your clients not just the application
but the entire operating system with all the
requirements and the application and then
ask your clients to run it within a hypervisor
you can run old applications that require
operating systems that are very old and you
don't want the maintain so you just have a
copy of that at
a virtual machine to run them we will see
that it's easier to migrate
services and operating systems since everything
is virtual you do not really around the stuff
it's not really installed on top of the
hardware but it's the hypervisor
it's easier to move one virtual machine from
one server with one hypervisor to a server
with another hypervisor if that
is what you have to do but of course here you
need to take into account that if the hardware
fails then you might be paying a very high
price because now the hypervisor will die
and all your operating systems will die and
I guess everyone is familiar with the term
cloud or the cloud and despite the fact that
many people have different opinions on what
exactly it is hopefully you can agree
with me here that if you think about virtualization
and you stretch it to the point in which you
actually
don't even buy the physical server but you
just connect to a server that runs an hypervisor
and delivers you different services different
operating systems that is basically the cloud